Guide to the Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States, New York Commandery Records 1894-2012 (bulk 1894-1960s) MS 3201
New-York Historical Society
Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States, New York Commandery records
1894-2012 (bulk 1894-1960s)
New-York Historical Society
Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States. New York Commandery
MS 3201
4.5 Linear feet in 4 record cartons, 1 document box, and 1 oversize folder
The collection includes membership applications from 1895-1963; foundational documents from the Military Order's inception in 1894-1895; meeting minutes and related documents for the organization's early decades through 1922; photographs of about 100 members (known as companions), including its Commanders from the early twentieth century; a history of the national organization self-published in 1997; and other items.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I. Applications for Companionship [Membership Applications], 1895-1963
Series II. Organizational Records, 1894-1997 (bulk 1895-1922)
Series III. Photographs and Graphic Material, 1917-2012 (bulk undated)
Series IV. Digitized Material, 1894-2012 (bulk 1894-1960s)
Biographical / Historical
The Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States, New York Commandery was formed in New York City in December 1894 by a group of veterans and descendants of officers of America's wars with foreign adversaries, specifically at the time the Revolution, War of 1812, War with Tripoli, and Mexican War. The organization was incorporated under the name Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York, but it was immediately determined that the name bore a resemblance to a similar organization in Massachusetts. Consequently, in 1895 the Order changed its name to its present form.
The foundational declaration, or "Institution," of the Order's charter members cited the purposes of the organization, which included honoring the memory of the veterans of America's foreign wars, strengthening ties of fellowship among the companions (as the Order's members are known), fostering the cultivation of military and naval science, and maintaining national honor, union and independence. A constitution was established which included the qualifications for membership. The specifics of these have changed over the course of the New York Commandery's history, sometimes in exclusionary ways, such as the institution of a Caucasian [sic] racial requirement after World War I (eliminated around 1962), and sometimes in inclusionary ways, such as the removal of a male lineage requirement, but the principal thread throughout is that officers or descendants of officers who served in a foreign military conflict are eligible.
The formation of the New York Commandery quickly served as a model, and Pennsylvania formed its own Commandery in 1895, followed by Connecticut in 1896 and then several other states. In response to this sudden proliferation, a National Commandery was formed in 1896. The New York Commandery held its own annual meeting; the National Commandery sponsored triennial (later biennial) conventions.
(The above note was based on materials in the collection and the website of the Military Order of Foreign Wars, New York Commandery's website.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly. Patrons may request view-only remote access to digital materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States, New York Commandery, 2021
Scope and Contents
The collection includes about 1,750 applications for companionship (i.e., membership applications) from 1895-1963, with the applicant's service record (or of his ancestor in the case of a hereditary companionship); foundational documents from the Military Order's inception in 1894-1895; meeting minutes and related documents for the organization's early decades through 1922; photographs of about 100 companions, including its Commanders from the early twentieth century; a history of the national organization self-published in 1997; and other items.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies of most of the documents in the collection were made by the Commandery and were included with the donation in 2021. These are expected to be made available in time through N-YHS's Digital Library, but can temporarily be made available upon request by contacting manuscripts@nyhistory.org. Only two items were included by the Commandery as digital-only documents: a list of members (Digital Folder 39) and a compiled history of the New York Commandery (Digital Folder 50).
Letters (correspondence); Membership application.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Societies -- New York (State); Veterans -- New York (State)
- Series I. Applications for Companionship [Membership Applications], 1895-1963; 3 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes the completed applications for veteran or hereditary companionship in numbered sequence from #1, submitted at the beginning of the organization in 1895, to #1750, dating from 1963. Later applications were not included in the donation to N-YHS.
  In addition to the applicant's basic identifying information, such as name, address, occupation, date and place of birth, the applications include the applicant's service record or, in the case of a hereditary companionship, the ancestor's service record and identifying information. Supplementary documents, such as letters of recommendation, are also included.
  The pre-printed application forms, which changed over time, include the various attestations required of a successful applicant, including some no longer required by the organization, such as being of the Caucasian race [sic] (from about 1918 to 1962) or that a hereditary applicant be of the male line of descent from the veteran.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in numerical order of the applications, which are roughly chronological by application date, bound in 20 volumes.
  - Applications #1-100, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
  - Applications #101-200, 1896-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 2)
  - Applications #201-301, 1899-1903 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 3)
  - Applications #302-402, 1903-1918 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 4)
  - Applications #403-503, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 5)
  - Applications #504-604, 1919-1920 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 6)
  - Applications #605-705, 1920 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 7)
  - Applications #706-806, 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 8)
  - Applications #807-901, 1922-1924 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 9)
  - Applications #902-1000, 1924-1928 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 10)
  - Applications #1001-1100, 1928-1936 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 11)
  - Applications #1101-1200, 1936-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 12)
  - Applications #1201-1300, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 13)
  - Applications #1301-1400, 1946 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 14)
  - Applications #1401-1450, 1946 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 15)
  - Applications #1451-1500, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 16)
  - Applications #1501-1550, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 17)
  - Applications #1551-1600, 1949-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 18)
  - Applications #1601-1650, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 19)
  - Applications #1651-1750, 1953-1963 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 20)
- Series II. Organizational Records, 1894-1997 (bulk 1895-1922); 1 Linear feet
  The series includes various organizational records, primarily foundational documents from the inception of the organization as the Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York, the court approval for the name change in 1895, and meeting minutes and related documents from the Military Order's early decades, through 1922. There are far fewer documents from the mid-late twentieth century, and these relate primarily to recipients of the organization's MacArthur Award in the 1960s-1980s and to the organization's anniversary celebrations in 1975 and 1994. The latter includes a congratulatory letter from U.S. President Bill Clinton. Opening the series is a self-published centennial history of the national organization.
  The series is arranged by subject matter.
  - "The Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States: History of the First One Hundred Years, 1894-1994, [with] Current Constitution and Membership Roster." Compiled by Captain Ronald E. Fischer, AUS, 1997 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York. Founding declaration, 1894-1895 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    Original declarations signed by the charter members establishing the organization.
  - Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York. Constitution, 1894? (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    Draft and final(?) constitution.
  - Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York. Certificate of Incorporation, 1895, 1913 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes the original certified copy of 1895 and a second copy certified in 1913. A third copy in the folder is a transcript of the 1913 certified copy.
  - Name change approval, 1895, 1912-1913 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    Original copy of the court approval for name change from Military and Naval Order of the United States in the State of New York to Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States; New York Commandery, with letter of acknowledgement from the Navy Department (1895), and a certified copy (1913) with related letter from the New York Secretary of State (1912).
  - National Commandery. Constitution, [1896] (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Law and regulation concerning military society badge, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    Letter from the Navy Department confirming that regulations permit the wearing of military society badges on ceremonial occasions by officers and enlisted men, and copy of the New York state law regulating the wearing of such badges.
  - Minutes of the Council, 1895-1902 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 1)
    Handwritten minutes.
  - Minutes of the Council, 1902-1907 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Minutes of the Council, 1908-1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of the Council, 1913-1916 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minutes of the Council, 1916-1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1894-1895 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 2)
    Handwritten minutes beginning with the first meeting of the organization in December 1894 and ending at December 1895. Includes both Council meeting minutes and membership meetings. Includes transcriptions of the founding declaration and the constitution.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1895-1903 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1905-1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Meeting documents, 1897 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes notes for minutes of the special meeting of October 27, 1897; report of the committee on a reception for the National Council; and biographical sketches of James W. Abert and Michael Moore.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1898 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes the Secretary's report in both original typed, signed form and in printed form; and reports of the committee to consider and draft an amendment to Article XI of the Constitution.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1899 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
    Includes Secetary's report for the annual meeting; stenographer's minutes of the annual meeting and the adjourned special meeting; and the Committee on Nominations adopted slate of candidates for office.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1900 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    Includes stenographer's report of the annual meeting; reports of the Council and of the Secretary at the meeting; report of the Committee on Revision of the Constitution; and report of the Committee on Nominations.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    Includes the proceedings (stenographer's report) of the annual meeting; the Secretary's report at the meeting; and the Treasurer's report, with a list of companions in arrears.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1902 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    Includes annotated list of members; Secretary's report to the annual meeting; and report of the annual meeting.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1903 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    Includes list of members (1902 list annotated for 1903 changes); printed announcement for the annual meeting; minutes of the annual meeting; secretary's report at the meeting; Council's report at the meeting; and treasurer's report.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    Includes minutes of the annual meeting and the reports of the secretary and of the Council at the meeting.
  - Annual meeting documents, 1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
  - 4th Triennial Convention documents, 1905 April (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    Includes seven letters regarding the appointments of delegates to the convention, a list of dinner attendees and payment record, and transcripts of four speeches (also referred to as toasts) made at the convention. Speeches were by General Alexander S. Webb concerning a proposed joint congressional resolution about the wearing of military society badges by military officers; Colonel George C. Cabell, Jr. of Virginia on the positive aspects of the expansion in the number of state commanderies, including increased patriotism across the United States, reconciliation between North and South, and an eager preparedness for the eventual wars certain to be fought by the U.S. to protect its foreign interests; Baron Kentaro Kaneko of the House of Peers of Japan concerning "the Moral Rules of the Japanese Army"; and Colonel Snowden of Pennsylvania, responding in part to Cabell, framing the role of the organization as patriotic, but in opposition to war and military conquest in favor of diplomacy and reconciliation.
  - Honorary Member nominations, 1945 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    Includes 3 carbon copies of letters: one to General Douglas MacArthur informing him of his nomination by the New York Commandery as an honorary member and asking if he will accept; and two letters to the National Commandery with the recommendations of honorary memberships for MaArthur and for Lieutenant General Jonathan M. Wainwright.
  - MacArthur Award (4 folders), 1961-1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26-29)
    Includes copy of the resolution establishing the award (1961) and documents related to the award program and recipient for various (though not all) years from 1962-85. Includes photographs of some recipients receiving the award, including General MacArthur (1962), Francis Cardinal Spellman (1963), Vice Admiral Harold T. Deutermann (1965), and Paul Volcker (1982). Other documents are press releases, clippings, nominations, event invitations, declined acceptances and nominations, and the like.
  - Mayoral proclamation. Oversize, 1975 (Box OS-Small)
    Commemorating its 80th anniversary, a proclamation that the week of May 12, 1975, was "Military Order of Foreign Wars Week." Signed by New York City Mayor Abraham D. Beame.
  - Centennial anniversary, 1994-1995 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    Includes congratulatory letters (1994) from U.S. President Bill Clinton, New York Governor Mario M. Cuomo, and New York City Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani; and two resolutions from the 42nd Biennial Convention (1995) acknowledging the death of Commander-General Chalmers Dale and his leadership of the centennial observance.
- Series III. Photographs and Graphic Material, 1917-2012 (bulk undated); .5 Linear feet
  The series is comprised primarily of almost 100 photographic portraits of companions from across the history of the organization. All are identified by name and, for most, their companion number. These range from one of the group's charter members (#3, James Henry Morgan) to a set of photographs taken in 1990-91 during Operation Desert Storm with member #1955, Christopher Arnheiter. These photographs are of various sizes, ranging from small snapshots to larger, matted poses. There is a roughly even split between those that picture companions in their military uniforms and those in civilian dress. Eleven of the portraits are of companions that served as the organization's Commander from 1910-1937; these are identified in the container list. The series also holds a few group photographs from some of the organization's events, including dinners and meetings, and other graphic materials. All items are identified to some extent in the container list.
  The series is arranged by subject, with portraits followed by events and miscellaneous topics. Portraits are generally arranged by size or other such feature.
  - Companions. Portraits, small, 1930s, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    Companions 105 (Betts), 176 (Perrine), 400 (Knauer), 428 (Whitney), 467 (Hitchcock, news clipping photo) 548 (Wallace), 581 (McLean), 617 (Crocker), 670 (Garrison), 692 (Ulrichs), 803 (Fiske), 1014 (Thierry, exceptionally small), 1016 (Pell, Jr)
  - Companions. Portraits, approximately 4x6 inches, 1930s, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    Includes 61, (Andrews), 205 (Parker), 281 (Kobbe), 407 (Mazet), 494 (Nexsan), 522 (Robinson), 682 (Hays), 707 (Sloan), 728 (Joyce), 742 (Bourne), 749 (Huddleson, Jr), 754 (Pederson), 802 (Bogert), 818 (Vermeule, Jr), 828 (Wells), 849 (Vanderbilt), 927 (Heckard), 978 (Goodwin), 988 (Hellweg), 1020 (Berg), 1038 (Hansen)
  - Companions. Portraits, approximately 6x9 inches, 1920s-1940s, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
    Includes 168 (Andrews), 217 (Emmet), 267 (Wood), 421 (Adams), 586 (Reynolds/Ruscovar), 676 (Cattus), 699 (Moore), 725 (Gibbons, photo of painting), 765 (Towns), 771 (Merrill, Jr), 831 (Knierim), 882 (Cronin), 901 (Bolles), 907 (Durand), 953 (Benjamin), 965 (Sellman), 1035 (Douglas), 1036 (Reichner), 1046 (Gardner), 1842 (Carman)
  - Companions. Portraits, approximately 8x11 inches, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
    Includes 360 (Cluett), 408 (Engel), 479 (Chauncey), 610 (Clarke, Jr), 644 (Rack), 734 (Merriman), 768 (Comfort), 781 (Lloyd), 845 (Gilbert), 911 (Stewart), 1019 (Albee), 1023 (Lovejoy), 1043 (Perkins)
  - Companions. Portraits, on boards or matted (medium size), undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
    Includes 79 (Falls), 358 (Forshew), 834 (Shepard), 942 (Langdon), 975 (Davis)
  - Companions. Portraits, unframed (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    These items were unframed for conservation reasons by N-YHS. Includes companions #3 (James Henry Morgan, one of the charter members, 1st Secretary General of the National Commandery), #304 (Amory Sibley Carhart, Commander, 1910-12), #145 (William Graves Bates, Commander, 1912-20), #397 (De Witt Clinton Weld, Commander, 1921-22), #390 (William Seaman Bainbridge, Commander, 1922-25), #455 (Paul Debevoise, Commander, 1925-26), #557 (Gustav Tuska, Commander, 1927-28), #970 (Pelham St. George Bissell, Commander, 1930-32), #875 (John H. Byrue, Commander, 1933-1935), #484 (Washington Irving Taylor, Commander, 1935), and #387 (John F. Daniell, Commander, 1936-37).
  - Companions. Portraits, oversize, 1920s?, 1934 (Box OS-Small)
    Includes companion #456 (David Banks, Commander, 1920-21) and #888 (John W. Morgan, Secretary General of National Commandery).
  - Companion 934 (Hoblitzell). Portrait, drawing, 1918 October 1 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
    Inscribed drawing by Joseph Cummings Chase
  - Companion 1955 (Arnheiter). Desert Storm (Iraq), 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
    Includes color photographs taken in the field during the war, several of tanks (member was in the 3rd Battalion, 41st Field Artillery, 24th Infantry Division. Two of the unit's "business cards" are with the photos.)
  - Companions, unknown number. Portraits., 1917, 1924, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
    Includes Ralph Earle, Henry Lyden, Albert Kann
  - Honorary companions, no number, 1975, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    Includes John F. O'Ryan, Joseph K. Kuhn, W.M. Wright, and Joseph Park Moorer (1975)
  - Events. Dinners, 1940, 1943, 1948 (Box OS-Small)
    Includes 3 panoramic photos: 46th annual dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria (1940), mess dinner of the European Commandry of the Military Order of Foreign Wars of the United States (1943), and dinner in honor of General Hugh A. Drum, retiring commanding general of the New York National Guard, held at the 7th Regiment Armory (1948)
  - Events. Annual banquet, 1974 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    Includes guest list as well as many photographs of the event.
  - Events. New York Commandery group photo, circa 1975 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
    Taken at Park Sheraton Hotel in 1974 or 1975
  - Events. Meetings/Banquets?, 1990, 1994, 1997 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
    Includes event snapshots (1990, 1994), speaker notes (1990), program for 1995 meeting with publicity photograph of featured speaker Angier Biddle Duke.
  - Events. President's Day celebration, 2008 February 21 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 43)
    Includes print-outs of digital photographs. The folder also has the CD of images; this is restricted from use in order not to corrupt the files. For access, make arrangements with the manuscripts curator at manuscripts@nyhistory.org.
  - Other events, 1930s-1980 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 44)
    Includes awards to West Point cadets (1936, 1980, undated) and commemoration at the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier (undated, but likely 1937)
  - Drawing, 1923 (Box OS-Small)
    Pen and ink drawing depicting military servicemen of various wars for the organization.
  - Photoreproduction of Saturday Evening Post cover, with inscription, 2012 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes reproduction of October 23, 1965, cover featuring the Medal of Honor recipient Captain Roger Donlon. Inscribed by Donlon in 2012, with accompanying texts. Item was unframed at N-YHS for conservation purposes.
  - Digital storage device (RESTRICTED) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 45)
    USB drive with digitized scans described in Series IV. This digital storage device is for staff back-up access only; not for research access. The digital files will be made accessible in time through the N-YHS digital library, but can temporarily be made available upon request by contacting manuscripts@nyhistory.org.
- Series IV. Digitized Material, 1894-2012 (bulk 1894-1960s); 73.7 Gigabytes 25,901 files (273 folders)
  This series is comprised of digitized versions (JPG and PDF) made by the Commandery and included with the donation in 2021. These are expected to be made available in time through N-YHS's Digital Library, but can temporarily be made available upon request by contacting manuscripts@nyhistory.org.
  Most of the documents in the collection were digitized and are available in both JPG and PDF format. Only two items were included by the Commandery as digital-only documents: a list of members (Digital Folder 39) and a compiled history of the New York Commandery (Digital Folder 50).
  - Annual Meeting Minutes Typewritten 14DEC1905 thru 8MAY1912, 278 Megabytes 80 files (Digital-folder 1)
  - Applications Ledger 1 thru 100, 1.79 Gigabytes 625 files (Digital-folder 2)
  - Applications Ledger 101 thru 200, 1.35 Gigabytes 476 files (Digital-folder 3)
  - Applications Ledger 201 thru 301, 1.23 Gigabytes 444 files (Digital-folder 4)
  - Applications Ledger 302 thru 402, 1.31 Gigabytes 482 files (Digital-folder 5)
  - Applications Ledger 403 thru 503, 1.35 Gigabytes 490 files (Digital-folder 6)
  - Applications Ledger 504 thru 604, 1.4 Gigabytes 498 files (Digital-folder 7)
  - Applications Ledger 605 thru 705, 1.79 Gigabytes 617 files (Digital-folder 8)
  - Applications Ledger 706 thru 806, 1.78 Gigabytes 621 files (Digital-folder 9)